在我们进入技术内容前
Before we start with the technical
material, I want to tell you a little bit
我想简要介绍一下密码学历史
David Kahn的解密者一书在这方面写得很漂亮
about the history of cryptography. There's
a beautiful book on this topic by David
它涵盖了自巴比伦时代以来的密码学历史
Kahn called the codebreakers. It covers
the history of cryptography all the way
我这里只为大家介绍
from the Babylonian era, to the
present. Here, I'm just going to give you
几例历史上的加密术
它们都已被严重地破解了
a few examples of historical ciphers, all
of which are badly broken. So to talk
在这之前，我首先要介绍我们的朋友
Alice和Bob
about ciphers the first thing I'm going to
do is introduce our friends Alice and Bob,
他们将陪伴我们整个学季
Alice和Bob正在试图
who are gonna be with us for the rest of
the quarter. So Alice and Bob are trying
安全地通信，有一个攻击者在窃听他们的会话
to communicate securely and there is an
attacker who's trying to eavesdrop on
为了安全通信，他们要共享一个密钥
their conversation. So to communicate
securely, they're going to share a secret
我记为K。双方都知道这个密钥
但是攻击者不知道密钥K
key, which I'll denote by K. They both know
the secret key. But the attacker does not
双方使用一个加密术
know anything about this key K.
So now they're gonna use a cipher, which
即一对算法，加密算法E
is a pair of algorithms, an
encryption algorithm denoted by E, and a
和解密算法D。这些算法如下工作：
decryption algorithm, D. These algorithms
work as follows: the encryption algorithm
加密算法E以信息M为输入，还要输入密钥K
E takes the message M as inputs. And it
takes as inputs, the key K. I'm gonna
我要在密钥输入上方放一个楔形
表示这个输入确实是密钥输入
put a wedge above the key input just
to denote the fact that this input is
然后加密算法输出密文
really the key input. And then it outputs
a ciphertext. Which is the encryption of
即为信息M使用密钥K加密的结果
我始终把密钥写在前面
the message M using the key K. I'm always
gonna write the key first. Now, and when I
当我写:=时，是定义变量C代表什么
write:= what I mean is that the
expression defines what C what the
现在密文经互联网传给Bob
variable C stands for. Now the ciphertext
is transmitted over the internet to Bob,
实际上它可以通过互联网传递
somehow. Actually it could be transmitted
over the internet. Could be transmitted
也可通过加密文件系统传递，这不重要
但是当密文到达Bob时
using an encrypted file system, it doesn't
really matter, but when the ciphertext
他可以把密文带入解密算法
reaches Bob, he can plug it into the
decryption algorithm and give the
使用同样的密钥K
我这里又放一个楔形
decryption algorithm the same key K.
Again, I'm gonna put a wedge here as well. To
以表示密钥输入，以及解密算法给出原文
denote the key inputs and the decryption
algorithm outputs the original plaintext
我们之所以说这些是对称加密
message. Now the reason we say that these
are symmetric ciphers is that both the
是因为加解密双方都使用了相同密钥K
本课程稍后我们会看到
encrypter and decrypter actually use the
same key K. As we'll see later
有些加密术是加解密双方使用不同密钥的
in the course, there are ciphers where the
encrypter uses one key and the decrypter
不过这里我们就关注对称加密
uses a different key. But here we're just
going to focus on symmetric cipher where
即双方使用相同密钥。好的
我来给几个历史上的加密例子
both sides use the same key. Okay, so let
me give you a few historic examples of
第一个例子，最简单的替换式密码
ciphers. The first example, the simplest
one is called the substitution cipher. I
我能肯定大家在幼儿园里玩过替换式密码
am sure all of you played the substitution
ciphers when you were in kindergarten.
替换式密码的密钥是一张替换表
Basically a key for a substitution cipher
is a substitution table that basically
告诉我们如何映射字母
比如这里字母A映射到C
says how to map our letters. So here for
example the letter A would be mapped to C,
B映射到W，C映射到N，等等
the letter B would be mapped to W the
letter C would be mapped to N so on and so
Z映射到A
forth and then the letter Z would be
mapped, say, to A. So this is one example
这是一个替换式密码的密钥
只要使用我们之前介绍的记法
of a key for a substitution cipher. So just
to practice the notation we introduced
使用这个密钥加密一个特定信息
before, the encryption of a certain
message using this key, let's say the
比如说信息是BCZA，使用这里的密钥加密
message is BCZA, the encryption of this
message using this key here would be, is
一次替换一个字母
所以B变W，C变N，Z变A
done by substituting one letter at a time.
So B becomes W, C becomes N, Z becomes A,
A变C。所以BCZA加密后是WNAC，即密文
and A becomes C. So the encryption of BCZA
is WNAC, and this defines the ciphertext.
类似的，我们解密时当然使用相同密钥
Similarly we can decrypt the ciphertext using the same key and of course
我们会还原原明文信息。好的。由于历史原因
we'll get back the original message.
Okay. So, just for historical
有一个替换式密码的例子
reasons, there is one example of something
that's related to the substitution cipher
叫凯撒加密。凯撒加密实际上并不是密码
called the Caesar cipher. The Caesar
cipher, actually, is not really a cipher
原因是它没有密钥。
凯撒加密是这样的
at all. And the reason is that it doesn't
have a key. What a Caesar cipher is, is
它是一个固定替换的替换式密码
basically a substitution cipher where the
substitution is fixed. Namely, it's a
它将字母移动三位，所以A变D,B变E，C变F，等等
shift by three. So A becomes D, B becomes
E, C becomes F and so on and so forth.
注意Y变B，Z变C
它是适用于所有明文的固定替换
What is it, Y becomes B and Z becomes C.
It's a fixed substitution that's applied
所以这并不是密码，因为没有密钥
to all plaintext messages. So, again,
this is not a cipher, because there is no
或说密钥固定。如果攻击者知道加密流程
key, the key is fixed. So if an attacker
knows how our encryption scheme works, he
他可以轻易解密。密钥不是随机的，所以
can easily decrypt the message. The key is
not random, and therefore, decryption is
只要知道原理，解密非常容易
very easy once you understand how the
scheme actually works. Okay, so now, let's
现在我们回到替换式密码
这里密钥是随机选择的
go back to the substitution cipher, where
the keys really are chosen at random, the
这个替换表是随机选择的
让我们看看如何破解替换式密码
substitution tables are chosen at random.
And let's see how we break this
破解非常容易。第一个问题是
substitution cipher. Turns out to be very
easy to break. The first question is, how
密钥空间有多大？也就是说有多少不同的密钥
big is the key space? How many different
keys are there, assuming we have 26
假设我们有26个字母。我希望大家都认为
答案是26的阶乘
letters? So, I hope all of you said that,
the number of keys is 26 factorial,
因为一个替换表形式的密钥
就是26个字母的一个排列
because, a key, a substitution key, is
simply a table, a permutation of all 26
26个字母的排列一共26的阶乘个
letters. The number of permutations of 26
letters, is 26 factorial. If you calculate
如果你算出来，26的阶乘约为2的88次方
this out, twenty-sixth factorial is about
two to the 88th, which means that
意味着描述一个替换密钥需要88位
describing a key in a substitution cipher
takes about 88 bits. So, each key is
所以每个密钥以88位表示
这个大小对密钥空间来说是很合适的
represented by about 88 bits. Now, this is
a perfectly fine size for a keyspace. In
事实上，我们将看到的完美安全或充分安全的密码
fact, we're gonna be seeing ciphers that
are perfectly secure, or, you know, that
其密钥空间也大概有这么大。但是
are adequately secure, with key spaces
that are roughly of this size. However,
即使替换式密码的密钥空间约2的88次方
even though the substitution cipher has a
large key space of size 2^88, it's
它依然是极不安全的。我们来看看如何破解之
still terribly insecure. So let's see how
to break it. And to break it, we're going
我们使用字母的频率来破解
第一个问题是，在英文文献中
to be using letter frequencies. So the
first question is, what is the most
什么字母出现频率最高？我想大家都知道
frequent letter in English text? So I
imagine all of you know that, in fact, E
E是事实上最常见的字母。如果我们将其量化
is the most common letter. And that is
gonna, if we make it quantitative, that's
它可以帮我们破解替换式密码。所以根据密文
gonna help us break a substitution cipher.
So just given the ciphertext, we can
我们就可以还原明文了。首先我们使用
already recover the plaintext. So the way
we do that is, first of all, using
英文字母的频率。这样办
frequencies of English letters. So here's
how this works. So you give me an
给我一个使用替换式加密的密文。我知道在明文中
encrypted message using the substitution
cipher. All I know is that the plaintext
字母E在英语中出现频率最高
is in English and I know that the letter E
is the most frequent letter in English.
事实上，它在标准英文文献中的出现频率约12.7%
And in fact, it appears 12.7 percent of
the time in standard English texts. So
所以我要做的就是看密文中各字母
what I'll do is I'll look at the ciphertext you gave me and I'm going to count
出现了多少次。现在，在密文中出现最多的字母
how many times every letter appears. Now
the most common letter in the ciphertext
以很高的概率是字母E的加密结果
is going to be the encryption of the
letter E with very high probability. So
所以现在我可以发现密钥替换表中的一项
now I'm able to recover one entry in the
key table. Mainly the letter, mainly now I
现在我知道E映射到哪了
英文中下一个常见字母是T
know what the letter E maps to. The
next, most common letter in English is the
出现频率约9.1%
letter T, that appears about 9.1 percent
of the time. So now again, I count how
我再次数一下密文中各字母出现次数第二多的字母
many times each letter appears in the
ciphertext. And the second most frequent
就很有可能是T的加密结果
letter is very likely to be the encryption
of the letter T. So now I've recovered a
所以我发现了密钥表里的第二项
我还可以继续，事实上
second entry in the key table. And I can
continue this way. In fact, the letter A
A是下一个常见字母，出现频率约8.1%
is the next most common letter; it appears
8.1 percent of the time. So now I can
所以现在我能猜出密文中第三常见字母
guess that the third most common letter in
the ciphertext is the encryption of the
是A的加密结果
现在我已经发现密钥表中的三项了
letter A. And now I've recovered three
entries in the key table. Well, so now
那么现在我该怎么办？
余下字母在英文里出现的次数差不多
what do I do? The remaining letters in
English appear roughly same amount of
除了一些罕见字母比如Q，X
我们在这里有点困住了
time, other than some rare letters like Q
and X. But we're kinda stuck at this
我们弄出了表里的三项，接下来怎么办？
point. We figured out three entries in
the key table but what do we do next? So,
接下来的方法是使用字母配对的频率
the next idea is to use frequencies of
pairs of letters. Sometimes these are
有时这些叫二合字母。我要计算各字母配对
called digrams. So, what I'll do is, I'll
count how many times each pair of letters
在密文中的出现次数
我知道在英语中，最常见的配对
appears in the cipher text, and, I know
that in English, the most common pairs of
有HE, AN, IN。我猜TH也是常见配对
letters are things like, HE, AN. IN, I
guess TH is another common pair of
所以我知道密文中的最常见配对
letters. And so I know that the most
common pair of letters in the ciphertext
可能是这四种配对之一的加密结果
is likely to be the encryption of one of
these four pairs. And so by trial and
经过尝试我能推出更多项。。。
得到更多项，就又能继续尝试
error I can sort of figure out more entry ...
more elements in the key table and again
三合字母了。实际上
by more trial and error this way by
looking at trigrams. I can actually figure
我可以推出整个表来
所以这里的基本事实是
out the entire key table. So the bottom
line here is that in fact the substitution
替换式密码对最艰苦的攻击形式：惟密文攻击
cipher is vulnerable to the worst possible
type of attack namely a ciphertext only
是脆弱的。仅凭密文攻击者就能还原密钥
attack. Just given the ciphertext the
attack that can recover the decryption key
以及还原明文
and therefore recover the original plaintext. So there's really no point in
所以使用替换式密码没有用
因为攻击者可以轻易破解之
encrypting anything using the substitution
cipher, because the attacker can easily
相当于直接发送明文了
decrypt it all; you might as well send
your plaintext completely in the clear.
现在我们快速来到文艺复兴时期
So, now we're gonna fast-forward to the
Renaissance, and, I guess we're moving
我猜我们从罗马时期直接到了文艺复兴时期
来看一下Vigener设计的密码
from the Roman Era to the Renaissance, and
look at a cipher designed by a fellow
Vigener生活在16世纪，其设计了一些密码
named Vigener, who lived in the
sixteenth century. He designed a couple
(更常见的法语拼法为Vigenère)
这里我展示其中一种的变体
of ciphers. Here I'm gonna show you a
variant of one of his ciphers, this is
叫Vigener加密。其密钥是一个单词
called a Vigener cipher. So, in a
Vigener cipher, the key is a
这里是CRYPTO,六个字母组成
word. In this case the word, is CRYPTO,
it's got six letters in it. And then to
加密一个信息，你把信息写在密钥下方
encrypt a message, what you do is, you
write the message under the key. So in
那么这里明文信息是“今天天不错”
然后你不断重复写密钥
this case the message is "WHAT A NICE DAY
TODAY" and then you replicate the key as
以覆盖整个信息，接着这样加密
many times as needed to cover the message.
And then the way you encrypt is basically,
将密钥字母和信息字母相加，模26
you add the key letters to the message
letters, modulo 26. So just to give
举个例子，Y加A，得到Z
you an example here, for example, if you
add Y and A, you get Z. If you add T and
T加A，得到U。对所有字母都这样做
记住加完以后取模26的余数
A, you get U. And you do this for all the
letters. And remember, whenever you add,
所以过了Z就回到A了
you add modulo 26. So if you go past Z,
you go back to A. So, that's the
这就是Vigener密码。事实上
解密和加密一样简单
Vigener cipher. And in fact,
decryption is just as easy as encryption.
解密时，把密文写在密钥下面
Basically, the way you would decrypt is,
again, you would write the ciphertext
重复写密钥，然后从密文中减去密钥
under the key. You would replicate the key
and then you would subtract the key from
就能得到明文。所以破解Vigener密码
the ciphertext to get the original plain
text message. So, breaking the Vigener
是很简单的。让我来展示怎么办
cipher is actually quite easy. Let me
show you how you do it. The first thing we
首先我们需要假设密钥长度已知
need to do is we need to assume that we
know the length of the key. So let's just
我们假设已知密钥长度。这里
密钥长度为6
assume we know that. In this case, the
length of the key is six. And then what we
然后我们把密文按照6个字母分组，怎么样？
do is we break the cipher text into groups
of six letters each, okay? So we're gonna
我们像这样得到了一组一组字母
每一组包含6个字母
get a bunch, a bunch of groups like this.
Each one, contains six letters. And then
然后我们看每组的第一个字母，怎么样？
we're gonna look at, the first letter in
each group. Okay? So, in this case, yes,
这里我们看第一个字母，每隔5个字母
we're looking at the first letter, every
six characters. Now, what do we know about
现在，这6个字母告诉我们什么？
事实上，它们都被同一个字母加密了
these six letters? We know that, in fact,
they're all encrypted using the same
所有这些都是用字母c加密的
letter in the ciphertext. All of these
are encrypted using the letter c. In other
换句话说，Z L W是明文移动3位
words. Z L W is a shift by three of the
plaintext letters. So if we collect all
如果我们收集所有这些字母
最常见的字母很可能是E的加密结果
these letters then the most common letter
among the set is likely to be the
对吧？E是英语里最常见的字母，所以
encryption of E, right? E is the most
common letter in English, therefore, if I
如果我每隔5个字母看，最常见的字母
look at every sixth letter, the most
common letter in that set is likely to be
很可能是E的加密，啊哈！
我们设想每隔5个字母
the encryption of the letter E. Ahah! So
let's just suppose that in fact the most
最常见的是H
common letter every sixth letter happens
to be the letter H. Then we know that E
然后我们知道E加上第一个字母等于H
也就是说第一个字母
plus the first letter of the key is equal
to H. That says that the first letter of
等于H减E，事实上就是C
the key is equal to H minus E. And in fact
that is the letter C. So now we've
所以我们找到了密钥的第一个字母
我们可以继续，找到第二个字母
recovered the first letter of the key. Now
we can continue doing this with the second
我们看每一组中第二个字母
letter. So we look at the second letter in
every group of six characters and again,
重复相同的操作，找出最常见字母
we repeat the same exercise. We find
the most common letter among the sets and
它很可能是字母E的加密结果
we know that the most, this most common
letter is likely the encryption of E and
所以不管最常见字母是什么
therefore whatever this letter, whatever
this most common letter is if we
把它减去E就是密钥的第二个字母
subtract 'E' from it we're going to get the
second letter of the key. And so on and so
这样继续看第三个。。。
我们还原整个密钥
forth. With, the third letter every six
characters. And this way we recover, the
这样就可以解密了
entire key. And that allows us to
decrypt, the message. Now, the only caveat
唯一要注意的是我假定我知道密钥长度了
is that I had to assume ahead of time that
I know the length of the key, which in
这里是6.但如果我们不知道密钥长度呢？
this case is six. But if I don't know the
length of the key ahead of time, that's
那也不是大问题。我运行这个解密过程
not a problem either. What I would do is I
would run this decryption procedure,
先假定密钥长度是1
然后假定长度是2，再运行解密过程
assuming the key length is one. Then I'd
run it assuming the key length is two.
然后假定长度是3，等等
Then I would run it assuming the key
lengths is three. And so on, and so on,
知道最后我得到一个信息，
一个说得通的信息
and so on, until finally I get a message.
I get a decryption that makes sense,
一旦做出来，我便知道我发现了正确的
that's sensical. And once I do that I know
that I've kind of recovered the right
密钥长度和正确的密钥
length of the key and I know that
I've also recovered the right key and
就能还原出正确的明文，对吧？
所以非常快地，你就能还原Vigener密码
therefore the right message. Okay? So
very, very quickly, you can recover, you
这还是惟密文攻击
can decrypt Vigener cyphers. Again,
this is a ciphertext only attack. The
有趣的是，Vigener有个好主意
interesting thing is, Vigener had a
good idea here. This addition mod
模26的和是个好主意，我们稍后还会看到
不过这里用的不好
26 is actually a good idea, and we'll see
that later, except it's executed very
我们会稍微修正一下
poorly here. And so we'll correct that, a
little bit later. Okay, we're gonna
好的，我们从文艺复兴时期快速来到19世纪
fast-forward now from the Renaissance to, to the nineteenth century where
电气化时代。人们希望设计电驱动的密码
everything became electric. And so people
wanted to design ciphers that use electric
特别地，这些密码叫做轴轮机
因为它们使用了轴轮
motors. In particular, these ciphers are
called rotor machines because they use
一个早期的例子叫Hibber机
它使用了单个电机
rotors. So an early example is called the
Hibber machine which uses a single motor.
这图就是Hibber机
这是电机，我猜轴轮在这
Here you have a picture of this machine.
The, the motor, the, I guess the rotor is
密钥在这个碟片里，嵌在碟片里
over here. And the secret key is captured
by this disc here, it's embedded inside of
你每按一次打字机，碟片转一个刻痕
this disc, which rotates by one notch
every time you press a key on the
怎么样？每按一次打字机，碟片转一个刻痕
typewriter, okay? So every time you, that
you hit a key, the disc rotates by one
这个密钥干什么呢？这个密钥
实际上是一个替换表的编码
notch. Now what does this key do? Well,
the key actually encodes a substitution
所以碟片实际上是密钥。我说过
table. So ... and therefore, the disc actually
is the secret key. And as I said, this
这个碟片编码了一张替换表
这里如果你第一个字母输入C
disc encodes a substitution table. In this
case, if you happen to press C as the
输出将会是字母T
然后碟片转一个刻痕
first letter, output would be the letter
T. And then the disc would rotate by one
转完后，新的替换表成这样了
notch. After rotating, rotating by one
notch, the new substitution table becomes
E移到上面去了
the one shown here. You see that E,
basically, moves up, and then the
余下的字母向下移
试想这是碟片旋转的二维体现
remaining letters move down. So imagine
this is basically a two dimensional
然后你按下第二个字母
rendering of the disc rotating by one
notch. Then you press the next letter. And
碟片再次旋转。注意到N移到上面
而其他字母向下移
the disc rotates again. You notice again N
moved up and the remaining letters moved
那么特别地，如果我们按C三次
down. So in particular, if we hit the
letter C three times, the first time we
第一次我们输出T，第二次输出S
would output, the output would be T, the
second time the output would be S, and the
第三次输出K
这就是单个轴轮机如何工作的
third time the output wold be K. So this
is how the single rotor machine works and
它一经提出后，很快就被破解
as it turned out very quickly after it was
advertised it was again broken basically
基本上使用字母频率，配对频率
和三合字母频率即可
using letter frequency, digram
frequencies and trigram frequencies. It's
只要密文够多，直接还原密钥和明文并不难
not that hard given enough ciphertext to
directly recover the secret key and then
还是惟密文攻击。为了抵抗这些
the message. Again, a ciphertext only
attack. So to kind of work against these
统计、频率攻击，这些轴轮机
frequency attacks, these statistical
attacks, these rotor machines became more
越来越复杂。最终，我相信
大家都听说过Enigma密码
and more complicated over time. Until
finally, I'm sure you've all heard of the
Enigma是一种复杂的轴轮机
Enigma. The Enigma is a kind of
complicated rotor machine. It uses
它使用了3、4或5个轴轮
Enigma机有多个不同版本
three, four, or five rotors. There are
different versions of the Enigma
这个例子是3个轴轮的Enigma机
machine. Here you see an example of the
Enigma machine with three rotors. The
Enigma机的密钥是轴轮的初始设定
secret key in the Enigma machine is the
initial setting of the rotors. Okay. So in
3个轴轮的情况有26个不同密钥
the case of three rotors there would be 26
cubed possible different keys. When you
在打字机上打字时
这些轴轮以不同速率旋转
type on the typewriter basically these
rotors here rotate at different rates.  Oh,
忘了说了，这图是4个轴轮的Enigma机
forgot to say this is a diagram of an Enigma
machine using four rotors. As you type on
你打字时，轴轮旋转，输出合适的字母
the typewriter the rotors rotate and
output the appropriate, letters of, the
即密文。所以这时密钥数为26的四次方
ciphertext. So in this case the number
of keys is 26 to the fourth, which is two
约2的18次方，密钥空间有点小
to the eighteen, which is relatively a
small key space. Today you can kind of,
现在你可以借助计算机暴力穷举
所有2的18次方个密钥
brute-force a search using a computer
through two to the eighteen different
以非常快的速度。你知道
我想我的手表只要几秒钟
keys, very, very quickly. You know, my
wristwatch can do it in just a few
就做完了。所以这个Enigma机
seconds, I guess. And so, these, this
Enigma machine was, already was using
使用了相对较小的密钥空间
大家肯定听说过英国密码学家
relatively small key spaces. But I'm sure
you've all heard that the British
在Bletchley Park曾发起对
Enigma机的惟密文攻击
cryptographers at Bletchley Park were
able to mount ciphertext only attacks on
他们在二战时能够破译德国的密码
the Enigma machine. They were able to
decrypt German ciphers back in World, in
在很多战斗中，它扮演了很重要的角色
World War Two. And that played an
important role in many different battles
战后，我想机械时代终结了
during the war. After the war, I guess
that was the end kind of the mechanical
计算机引领的数字时代来临了
age and started the digital age where
folks were using computers. And as the
随着世界上开始使用计算机
政府意识到要从工业界
world kind of migrated to using computers,
the government realized that it's buying a
购买大量设备，所以他们希望工业界
lot of digital equipment from industry.
And so they wanted industry to use a good
使用好的密码，这样购买设备时
cipher so that when it buys equipment from
the, from industry, it would be getting
就能得到很好的保密性。同时
政府还请求制定
equipment with, with a decent cipher. And
so the government put out this request for
一个数据加密标准
一个联邦数据加密标准
proposal for a data encryption standard,
a Federal data encryption standard. And
在今后课程中，我们将更多地讨论这方面工作
we're gonna talk about this effort, in
more detail later on in the course, but in
不过1974年的IBM提出的DES加密标准
1974 a group at IBM put together a cipher
that became known as DES, data encryption
成为一个联邦数据加密标准
standard, which became a Federal standard
for encrypting data. The key space for DES
DES的密钥空间为2的56次方
现在看来很小了
is two to the 56, which is relatively
small these days, but was large enough
不过在1974年是很大了
DES的另一个有趣的事情是
back in 1974. And another interesting
thing about DES is, rather than, unlike
它不像轴轮机一次加密一个字母
rotor machines which encrypt one character
at a time, the data encryption standard
这个加密标准一次加密64位
也就是一次8个字母
encrypts 64 bits at a time, namely eight
characters at a time. And we'll see the
我们将在本课程稍后看到这个的重要性
significance of this later on in the
course. Because DES uses such
因为DES的密钥空间很小，
今天我们可以使用暴力搜索
a small key space, these days it can be
broken by a brute-force search and so
所以现在DES是不安全的
工程项目中不能使用了
these days DES is considered
insecure and should not be used in
不幸的是，它在某些系统还有遗留
projects. Unfortunately, it is used in
some legacy systems, but it definitely is
不过逐步被淘汰中，在新项目中绝对不能用
on its way out and definitely should not
be used in new projects. Today there are
如今有了新的密码，比如高级加密标准
new ciphers, things like the advanced
encryption standard which uses 128 bit
使用128位密钥。我们稍后将讨论
高级加密标准的更多细节
keys. Again, we'll talk about the advanced
encryption standards in much more detail
还有很多其他类型的密码
later on in the course. There are many,
many other types of ciphers. I mentioned
比如Salsa20，稍后介绍之
这只是快速介绍了密码的历史
Salsa20 here. We'll see why in just a
minute. But this is all for the quick
现在我们可以进入更技术的内容了
historical survey and now we can get into
the more technical material.